# Simon Liu

Postbaccalaureate Fellow, National Human Genome Research Institute. NIHBC 10 - CRC BG RM 3-2551

10 Center Dr

Bethesda, MD 20892

且 simon.liu@nih.gov - ▼ nhgri/mgb

☑ simon@simonliu.dev - 😚 simonliu.dev

• github/simonliu99 - • orcid/0000-0002-1182-5492

🛅 linkedin/simonliu99 - 🗏 google/scholar

### Summary

I am a postbaccalaureate IRTA fellow at the National Institutes of Health interested in deep learning algorithms that improve patient outcomes. My recent work involves applying natural language processing to public and private datasets to build models for extracting patient and language annotators. I am a member of the Medical Genomics Unit at the National Human Genome Research Institute.

### Education

B.S., Biomedical Engineering, Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, MD.

08/2017 - 05/2021

Also completed B.S. major requirements for Computer Science Honors: Upsilon Pi Epsilon, general honors, Dean's list

GPA: 3.69

# Research Experience

Care Coordinator, Pan Asian Volunteer Health Clinic, Chinese Culture and Community Service Center, 10/2021 - present Gaithersburg, MD.

With Kate Lu and Yaoyao Zhu

Postbaccalaureate Fellow, National Human Genome Research Institute, Bethesda, MD. 07/2021 - present

With Benjamin Solomon

Software Engineer, Neuroplastic Surgery Research Laboratory, Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, 02/2020 - 05/2021

MD, USA.

With Chad Gordon.

Received Provost's Undergraduate Research Award 2020-21 [award] [news]

Laboratory Assistant, STAR-ORC, University of Maryland School of Medicine, Baltimore, MD, USA. 07/2018 - 03/2020

With Junfang Wu

Research Analyst, School of Medicine, Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, MD, USA. 12/2018 - 03/2020

With Susan Hutfless

Research Assistant, Battle Lab, Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, MD, USA. 02/2018 - 09/2018

With Alexis Battle and Ben Strober

## **Publications**

A list is also available on Google Scholar and Publons.

Journal Articles

Duong, D., Hu, P., Tekendo-Ngongang, C., Hanchard, S. E., **Liu, S.**, Solomon, B. D., & Waikel, R. L. (2022). Neural networks for classification and image generation of aging in genetic syndromes. Frontiers

in Genetics, 13. https://doi.org/10.3389/fgene.2022.864092

Li, Y., Ritzel, R. M., Khan, N., Cao, T., He, J., Lei, Z., Matyas, J. J., Sabirzhanov, B., **Liu, S.**, Li, H., Stoica, B. A., Loane, D. J., Faden, A. I., & Wu, J. (2020). Delayed microglial depletion after spinal cord injury reduces chronic inflammation and neurodegeneration in the brain and improves neurological recovery in

male mice. Theranostics, 10(25), 11376–11403. https://doi.org/10.7150/thno.49199

Li, Y., Ritzel, R. M., He, J., Cao, T., Sabirzhanov, B., Li, H., **Liu, S.**, Wu, L. J., & Wu, J. (2021). The voltage-gated proton channel Hv1 plays a detrimental role in contusion spinal cord injury via extracellular acidosis-mediated neuroinflammation. Brain, behavior, and immunity, 91, 267–283.

https://doi.org/10.1016/j.bbi.2020.10.005

# Conference Papers

Kenet, A., Mahadevan, E., Elangovan, S., Yan, J., Siddiq, K., **Liu, S.**, Ladwa, A., Narayanan, R., Dakkak, J., Benassi, T., Ng, K., & Manbachi, A. (2020). Flexible piezoelectric sensor for real-time image-guided colonoscopies: a solution to endoscopic looping challenges in clinic. Proc. SPIE 11315, Medical Imaging

C-1

J-3

J-2

1 - 1

	11ttp3.77d01.01g/ 10.11117712.2540070	
Meeting Abstracts	Hutfless, S. M., Chu, D., <b>Liu, S.</b> , & Kalloo, A. N. (2020). Predictors of ERCP-associated infections in outpatient hospitals. Gastrointestinal Endoscopy, 91(6). https://doi.org/10.1016/j.gie.2020.03.3314	A-2
	Hutfless, S. M., Chen, PH., Miller, S. D., Josephson, M., Joseph, S., Urrunaga, N., Kedia, S., <b>Liu, S.</b> , Arya, N., Hobstetter, L., Persad, P., Yeretssian, G., & Brant, S. R. (2020). Would K50* by any other name smell so sweet? A systematic review of claims-based Crohn's disease case definitions. Gastroenterology, 158(6). https://doi.org/10.1016/s0016-5085(20)31712-1	A-1
In Submission	Ledgister Hanchard, S.*, Dwyer, M.C.*, <b>Liu, S.</b> *, Hu, P., Tekendo-Ngongang, C., Waikel, R.L., Duong, D., & Solomon, B.D. Scoping review and classification of deep learning in medical genetics. [Accepted]. *Equal contributions.	S-1
Presentations	<b>Liu, S.*</b> , Ledgister Hanchard, S.*, Dwyer, M.C.*, , Hu, P., Tekendo-Ngongang, C., Waikel, R.L., Duong, D., & Solomon, B.D. Applications of deep learning in medical genetics. Poster presented at: NIH Virtual Postbac Poster Day 2022; Bethesda, MD. *Equal contributions. [poster]	P-1
Selected Honors	<b>Linda Trinh Memorial Award</b> , Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, MD, USA  Project: COVID-19 PPE Manufacturing Proposal: Consortium for 3D-Printed Headbands for Face Shields [ar With Y. Bai, J. Feitelberg, K. Hu, S. Kumar, K. Leo, J. Li, C. Shallal, and N. Zhang	05/2021 ticle]
	Intuitive Surgical Best Project Award Runner Up, Deep Learning course, Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, MD, USA.	12/2020
	Project: Detection and Segmentation of Pneumothoraces in Chest X-ray. [report] [ppt] [award] With F. Shao, Y. Huang, and A. Harmalkar.	
	<b>Provost's Undergraduate Research Award</b> , Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, MD, USA. Project: Implementing Electronic Beam Steering in an Implantable Ultrasound Device [award] [news] With Chad Gordon.	11/2020
	<b>Upsilon Pi Epsilon</b> , Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, MD, USA. International Honor Society for the Computing and Information Disciplines	10/2020
	Maryland Seal of Biliteracy, Maryland State Department of Education, Rockville, MD, USA.	06/2017
Selected Press	Stokel-Walker, Chris. "Amid war fears, archivists are racing to preserve Ukraine's internet" Input Mag. February 18, 2022.	2022
	Calabresi, Kaitlyn. "Interview with Health 3D" TCO Labs. November 20, 2019.  Sangana, Neha. "Conference highlights student startups in Md." The Johns Hopkins News-Letter.  November 15, 2018.	2019 2018
Selected Coursework	Computer Integrated Surgery I Computer Integrated Surgery II Machine Learning Machine Learning: Deep Learning Biomedical Data Science Precision Care Medicine I Precision Care Medicine II Foundations of Computational Biology and Bioinformatics	
Extracurricular Experience		3/2020 - 05/2021 1/2018 - 05/2021
Metadata	This document lives online at https://simonliu.dev/markdown-cv/. A downloadable version can be found at https://simonliu.dev/files/liu_cv.pdf.	

Based on markdown-cv by Eliseo Papa with styles based on David Whipp.

MIT License.

2020: Image-Guided Procedures, Robotic Interventions, and Modeling, 1131520 (16 March 2020).

https://doi.org/10.1117/12.2548873

Last updated: May 2022